The Great Gatsby chapter 1.
In my younger and more vulnerable years my father gave me some advice that I’ve
been turning over in my mind ever since.
“Whenever you feel like criticizing anyone,” he told me, “just remember that all
the people in this world haven’t had the advantages that you’ve had.”
He didn’t say anymore but we’ve always been unusually communicative in a reserved way,
and I understood that he meant a great deal more than that.
In consequence, I’m inclined to reserve all judgments a habit that has opened up
many curious natures to me and also made me the victim of not a few veteran boers
The abnormal mind is quick to detect and attach itself to this quality when it
appears in a normal person, and so it came about that in college I was
unjustly accused of being a politician, because I was privy to the secret griefs
of wild, unknown men.
Most of the confidences were unsought— —frequently I have feigned sleep,
preoccupation, or a hostile levity when I realized by some unmistakable sign that
an intimate revelation was quivering on the horizon; for the intimate revelations of young
men, or at least the terms in which they expressed them, are usually plagiaristic
and marred by obvious suppressions.
Reserving judgments is a matter of infinite hope.
I am still a little afraid of missing something if I forget that, as my father
snobbishly suggested, and I snobbishly repeat, a sense of the fundamental decencies is
parceled out unequally at birth.
And, after boasting this way of my tolerance, I come to the admission that it has a limit.
Conduct may be founded on the hard rock or the wet marshes, but after a certain
point I don’t care what it’s founded on.
When I came back from the East last autumn I felt that I wanted the world to
be in uniform and have a sort of moral attention forever; I wanted no more
riotous excursions with privileged glimpses into the human heart.
Only Gatsby, the man who gives his name to this book, was exempt from my reaction— —Gatsby,
who represented everything for which I have an unaffected scorn.
If personality is an unbroken series of successful gestures,
then there was something gorgeous about him, some heightened sensitivity to the
promises of life, as if he were related to one of those intricate machines that
register earthquakes 10 000 miles away.
This responsiveness had nothing to do with that flabby impressionability which
is dignified under the name of the “creative temperament”—
”—it was an extraordinary gift for hope, a romantic readiness such as I have
never found in any other person and which it is not likely I shall ever find again.
No— —Gatsby turned out all right in the end; it is what prayed on Gatsby,
what foul dust floated in the wake of his dreams that temporarily closed out
my interest in the abortive sorrows and short-winded elations of men.
My family have been prominent well to do people in this Middle Western city for
three generations. The caraways are something of a clan, and we have a
tradition that we’re descended from the Dukes of buckloo but the actual founder
of my line was my grandfather’s brother, who came here in 51 sent a substitute to
the Civil War, and started the wholesale hardware business that my father carries on today.
I never saw this great uncle but I’m supposed to look like him— —with special
reference to the rather hard-boiled painting that hangs in father’s office.
I graduated from New Haven in 1915, just a quarter of a century after my father,
and a little later I participated in that delayed Teutonic migration known as the Great War.
I enjoyed the counter raid so thoroughly that I came back restless. Instead of
being the warm center of the world of the Middle West now seemed like the
ragged edge of the universe— —so I decided to go East and learn the bond business.
Everybody I knew was in the bond business, so I supposed it could support one more single man.
All my aunts and uncles talked it over as if they were choosing a prep school
for me, and finally said, “Why yes with very grave, hesitant faces.
Father agreed to finance me for a year, and after various delays I came East,
permanently, I thought, in the spring of 22.
The practical thing was to find rooms in the city, but it was a warm season, and I
had just left a country of wide lawns and friendly trees, so when a young man
at the office suggested that we take a house together in a commuting town, it
sounded like a great idea.
He found the house, a weather beaten cardboard bungalow at 80 a month,
but at the last minute the firm ordered him to Washington, and I went out to the
country alone.
I had a dog— —at least I had him for a few days until he ran away—
—and an old Dodge and a Finnish woman, who made my bed and cooked breakfast and
muttered Finnish wisdom to herself over the electric stove.
It was lonely for a day or so until one morning some man, more recently arrived
than I, stopped me on the road.
“How do you get to West Egg village?” he asked helplessly.
I told him.
And as I walked on I was lonely no longer. I was a guide, a pathfinder, an
original settler.
He had casually conferred on me the freedom of the neighborhood
And so with the sunshine and the great bursts of leaves growing on the trees,
just as things grow in fast movies, I had that familiar conviction that life
was beginning over again with the summer.
There was so much to read, for one thing, and so much fine health to be pulled out
of the young breath-giving air.
I bought a dozen volumes on banking and credit and investment securities, and
they stood on my shelf in red and gold like new money from the mint, promising
to unfold the shining secrets that only Midas and Morgan and messiness knew. And
I had the high intention of reading many other books besides.
I was rather literary in college— —one year I wrote a series of very solemn
and obvious editorials for the Yale News— —and now I was going to bring back all
such things into my life and become again that most limited of all specialists,
the “well-rounded man.” This isn’t just an epigram— —life is much more successfully looked at
from a single window, after all.
It was a matter of chance that I should have rented a house in one of the
strangest communities in North America.
It was on that slender riotous island which extends itself due east of New
York— —and where there are, among other natural curiosities, two unusual formations of land
20 miles from the city a pair of enormous eggs, identical in contour and
separated only by a courtesy bay jot out into the most domesticated body of salt
water in the Western hemisphere, the great wet barnyard of Long Island Sound
they're not perfect ovals— —like the AG in the Columbus story they're both crushed
flat at the contact end— —but their physical resemblance must be a source of
perpetual confusion to the goals that fly overhead.
To the wingless a more arresting phenomenon is their dissimilarity in
every particular except shape and size.
I lived at West Egg, the— —well, the less fashionable of the two, though this is a
most superficial tag to express the bizarre and not a little sinister contrast between them.
My house was at the very tip of the egg, only 50 yards from the Sound, and
squeezed between two huge places that rented for 12 or 15 000 a season.
The one on my right was a colossal affair by any standard— —it was a factual
imitation of some Hotel Deville in Normandy, with a tower on one side,
spanking new under a thin beard of raw ivy, and a marble swimming pool, and more
than 40 acres of lawn and garden.
It was Gatsby’s mansion.
Or, rather, as I didn’t know Mr. Gatsby, it was a mansion inhabited by a gentleman
of that name.
My own house was an eyesore, but it was a small eyesore, and it had been overlooked,
so I had a view of the water, a partial view of my neighbor's lawn, and the
consoling proximity of millionaires— —all for eighty dollars a month.
Across the courtesy bay the white Palace is a fashionable East Egg glittered
along the water, and the history of the summer really begins on the evening I
drove over there to have dinner with the Tom Buchanans.
Daisy was my second cousin once removed, and I’d known Tom in college. And just
after the war I spent two days with them in Chicago.
Her husband, among various physical accomplishments, had been one of the most
powerful ends that ever played football at New Haven— —a national figure in a way,
one of those men who reached such an acute limited excellence at 21 that
everything afterwards savers of anti-climax His family were enormously wealthy— —even
in college his freedom with money was a matter for approach but now he’d left
Chicago and come East in a fashion that rather took your breath away: for
instance, he’d brought down a string of polo ponies from Lake Forest. It was hard
to realize that a man in my own generation was wealthy enough to do that.
Why they came East I don’t know.
They had spent a year in France for no particular reason, and then drifted here
and there unrestfully wherever people played polo and were rich together.
This was a permanent move, said Daisy over the telephone, but I didn’t believe it—
—I had no sight into Daisy’s heart, but I felt that Tom would drift on forever
seeking, a little wistfully, for the dramatic turbulence of some irrecoverable football game.
And so it happened that on a warm windy evening I drove over to East Egg to see
two old friends whom I scarcely knew at all.
Their house was even more elaborate than I expected, a cheerful red and white
Georgian Colonial mansion, overlooking the bay.
The lawn started at the beach and ran toward the front door for a quarter of a
mile, jumping over sundials and brick walks and burning gardens— —finally when
it reached the house drifting up the side in bright vines as though from the
momentum of its run.
The front was broken by a line of front windows, glowing now with reflected gold
and wide open to the warm windy afternoon, and Tom Buchanan in riding clothes was
standing with his legs apart on the front porch.
He had changed since his New Haven years.
Now he was a sturdy straw-haired man of 30 with a rather hard mouth and a supercilious manner.
Two shining arrogant eyes had established dominance over his face and
gave him the appearance of always leaning aggressively forward.
Not even the effeminate swank of his riding clothes could hide the enormous power of that body—
—he seemed to fill those glistening boots until he strained the top lacing, and you
could see a great pack of muscle shifting when his shoulder moved under
his thin coat. It was a body capable of enormous leverage— —a cruel body. His
speaking voice, a gruff husky tenor, added to the impression of fractiousness he conveyed.
There is a touch of paternal contempt in it, even toward the people he liked— —and
there were men at New Haven who hated his guts.
“Now, don’t think my opinion on these matters is final,” he seemed to say, “just
because I’m stronger and more of a man than you are.”
We were in the same senior society, and while we were never intimate I always
had the impression that he approved of me and wanted me to like him with some
harsh, defiant wistfulness of his own.
We talked for a few minutes on the sunny porch.
“I’ve got a nice place here,” he said, his eyes flashing about restlessly. Turning
me around by one arm, he moved abroad flat hand along the front vista,
including its sweep a sunken Italian garden, a half acre of deep, pungent roses,
and a snub-nosed motorboat that bumped the tide offshore.
“It belonged to domain the oil man.” He turned me around again, politely and abruptly.
“We’ll go inside.” We walked through a high hallway into a bright Rosy colored space
fragily bound into the house by French windows at either end.
The windows were a jar and gleaming white against the fresh grass outside
that seemed to grow a little way into the house.
A breeze blew through the room blue curtains in at one end and out the other
like pale flags, twisting them up toward the frosted wedding cake of the ceiling,
and then rippled over the wine colored rug, making a shadow on it as wind does
on the sea.
The only completely stationary object in the room was an enormous couch on which
two young women were buoyed up as though upon an anchored balloon.
They were both in white, and their dresses were rippling and fluttering as
if they had just been flown back in after a short flight around the house.
I must have stood for a few moments listening to the whip and snap of the
curtains and the groan of a picture on the wall there was a boom as Tom Buchanan shut
the rear windows and the caught wind died out about the room, and the curtains
and the rugs and the two young women ballooned slowly to the floor.
The younger of the two was a stranger to me. She was extended full length at her
end of the Devon completely motionless, and with her chin a little raised as if
she were balancing something on it which was quite likely to fall.
If she saw me out of the corner of her eyes she gave no hint of it—
—indeed, I was almost surprised into murmuring an apology for having disturbed her by coming in.
The other girl, Daisy, made an attempt to rise— —she leaned slightly forward with a
conscientious expression— —then she laughed and absurd, charming little laugh,
and I laughed too and I came forward into the room.
“I’m paralyzed with happiness.” She laughed again, as if she said something very
witty, and held my hand for a moment, looking up into my face, promising that
there was no one in the world she so much wanted to see.
That was a way she had.
She hinted in a murmur that the surname of the balancing girl was Baker.
(I’ve heard it said that Daisy’s murmur was only to make people lean toward her;
an irrelevant criticism that made it no less charming.)
At any rate, Miss Baker’s lips fluttered, she nodded at me almost imperceptibly,
and then quickly tipped her head back again— —the object she was balancing had
obviously taught it a little and given her something of a fright.
Again a sort of apology arose to my lips.
Almost any exhibition of complete self-sufficiency draws a stunned tribute from me.
I looked back at my cousin, who began to ask me questions in her low, thrilling voice.
It was the kind of voice that the ear follows up and down, as if each speech is
an arrangement of notes that will never be played again.
Her face was sad and lovely with bright things in it, bright eyes and a bright
passionate mouth, but there was an excitement in her voice that men who had
cared for her found difficult to forget: a singing compulsion, a whispered
“Listen,” a promise that she had done gay, exciting things just a while since and
that they were gay, exciting things hovering in the next hour.
I told her how I had stopped off in
Chicago for a day on my way East, and how a dozen people had sent their love
through me.
“Do they miss me?” she cried ecstatically.
“The whole town is desolate. All the cars have the left rear wheel painted black
as a morning wreath, and there’s a persistent whale all night along the
north shore.” “How gorgeous! Let’s go back, Tom. Tomorrow!”
Then she added relevantly You ought to see the baby.” “I’d like to.” “She’s asleep.
She’s three years old. Haven’t you ever seen her?” “Never.” “Well, you ought to see her.
She’s—” Tom Buchanan, who had been hovering restlessly about the room, stopped and
rested his hand on my shoulder.
“What you doing, Nick?” “I’m a bond man.” “Who with?” I told him. “Never
heard of them,” he remarked decisively.
This annoyed me.
“You will,” I answered shortly. “You will if you stay in the East
or I’ll stay in the East, don’t you worry,”
he said, glancing at Daisy and then back at me, as if he were alert for something
more. “I’d be a goddamn fool to live anywhere else.” At this point Miss Baker
said: “Absolutely!” with such suddenness that I started— —it was the first word she
uttered since I came into the room.
Evidently it surprised her as much as it did me, for she yawned and with a series
of rapid deaf movements stood up into the room.
“I’m stiff,” she complained, “I’ve been lying on that sofa for as long as I can
remember.” “Don’t look at me,” Daisy retorted, “I’ve
been trying to get you to New York all afternoon.” “No, thanks,” said Miss Baker to the four
cocktails just in from the pantry. “I’m absolutely in training.” Her host looked
at her incredulously. “You are!” He took down his drink as if it were a
drop in the bottom of a glass.
“How you ever get anything done is beyond me.” I looked at Miss Baker, wondering what
it was she “got done.” I enjoyed looking at her. She was a slender small breasted
girl, with an erect carriage, which she accentuated by throwing her body
backward at the shoulders like a young cadet. Her gray sun-strained eyes looked
back at me with polite reciprocal curiosity out of a wand charming, discontented face.
It occurred to me now that I had seen her, or a picture of her, somewhere before.
“You live in West Egg,” she remarked contemptuously. “I know somebody there.” “I
don’t know a single—” “You must know Gatsby.” “Gatsby?” demanded Daisy. “What Gatsby?” Before
I could reply that he was my neighbor dinner was announced; wedging his tense arm imperatively
undermined Tom Buchanan compelled me from the room as though he were moving a
checker to another square.
Slenderly, languidly, their hands set lightly on their hips, the two young
women preceded us out onto Rosy colored porch opened toward the sunset, where
four candles flickered on the table in the diminished wind.
“Why candles objected Daisy, frowning. She snapped them out with her fingers. “In two
weeks it’ll be the longest day in the year.” She looked at us all radiantly. “Do you
always watch for the longest day of the year and then miss it? I always watch for
the longest day in the year and then miss it.” “We ought to plan something,”
yawned Miss Baker, sitting down at the tables if she were getting into bed. “All
right,” said Daisy what do we plan?” She turned to me helplessly: “What do people plan?”
Before I could answer her eyes fastened with an odd expression on her little
finger. “Look!” she complained; “I heard it.” We all looked— —the knuckle was black and
blue. “You did it, Tom,” she said accusingly.
“I know you didn’t mean to, but you did do it.
That’s what I get for marrying a brute of a man, a great, big, hulking physical
specimen of a—” “I hate the word ‘hulking,’ objected Tom Crossley even in kidding.”
“Hulking,” insisted Daisy.
Sometimes she and Miss Baker talked at once, unobtrusively and with a bantering
in consequence that was never quite chatter, that was as cool as their white
dresses and their impersonal eyes in the absence of all desire.
They were here, and they accepted Tom and me, making only a polite pleasant effort
to entertain or to be entertained. They knew that presently dinner would be over
and a little later the evening too would be over and casually put away.
It was sharply different from the West, where an evening was hurried from phase
to phase toward its clothes in a continually disappointed anticipation
or else in sheer nervous dread of the moment itself.
“You make me feel uncivilized, Daisy,” I confessed on my second glass of corky
but rather impressive claret. “Can’t you talk about crops or something?” I meant
nothing in particular by this remark, but it was taken up in an unexpected way
civilization is going to pieces,” broke out Tom violently. “I’ve gotten to be a
terrible pessimist about these things.
Have you read The Rise of the colored Empires by this man Goddard?”
“Why, no,” I answered, rather surprised by his tone. “Well, it’s a fine book, and
everybody ought to read it. The idea is if we don’t look out the white race will
be— —will be utterly submerged. It’s all scientific stuff; it’s been proved.”
“Tom’s getting very profound,” said Daisy, with an expression of unthoughtful
sadness. “He reads deep books with long words in them. What was that word we—” “Well,
these books are all scientific,” insisted Tom, glancing at her impatiently. “This
fellow has worked out the whole thing.
It’s up to us, who are the dominant race, to watch out or these other races will
have control of things.” “We’ve gotta beat them down,” whispered
Daisy, winking ferociously toward the fervent sun. “You ought to live in
California—” began Miss Baker, but Tom interrupted her by shifting heavily in his chair
the idea is that we’re Nordics. I am, and
you are and and you are, and—” After an infinitesimal hesitation he included
Daisy with a slight nod, and she winked at me again. “—And we’ve produced all the
things that go to make civilization— —oh, science and art, and all about you Do you
see?” There was something pathetic in his concentration, as if his complacency, more
acute than of old, was not enough to him anymore When, almost immediately, the telephone
rang inside and the butler left the porch Daisy seized upon the momentary
interruption and leaned towards me. “I’ll tell you a family secret,” she whispered
enthusiastically. “It’s about the butler’s nose. Do you want to hear about the butler’s nose?”
“That’s why I came over tonight.” “Well, he wasn’t always a butler; he used
to be the silver polisher for some people in New York that had a silver
service for 200 people. He had to polish it from morning till night, until finally
it began to affect his nose—” “Things went from bad to worse,” suggested
Miss Baker. “Yes. Things went from bad to worse, until finally he had to give up his position.”
For a moment the last sunshine fell with romantic affection upon her glowing face;
her voice compelled me forward breathlessly as I listened— —then the glow
faded, each light deserting her with lingering regret, like children leaving a
pleasant street at dusk.
The butler came back and murmured something close to Tom’s ear, whereupon
Tom frowned, pushed back his chair, and without a word went inside.
As if his absence quickened something within her, Daisy leaned forward again,
her voice glowing and singing. “I love to see you at my table, Nick. You remind me
of uh of a rose, an absolute rose. Doesn’t he turned to Miss Baker for confirmation: “An
absolute rose?” This was untrue I'm not even faintly like a rose. She was only extemporizing,
but a stirring warmth flowed from her, as if her heart was trying to come out to
you concealed in one of those breathless, thrilling words.
Then suddenly she threw her napkin on the table and excused herself and went into the house.
Miss Baker and I exchanged a short glance consciously devoid of meaning.
I was about to speak when she sat up alertly and said shhh in a warning voice.
A subdued impassioned murmur was audible in the room beyond, and Miss Baker leaned
forward unashamed, trying to hear.
The murmur trembled on the verge of coherence, sank down, mounted excitedly,
and then ceased altogether uh This Mr. Gatsby you spoke of is my
neighbor I said Don’t talk. I want to hear what happens.” “Is something happening?” I inquired
innocently.
“You mean to say you don’t know?” said Miss Baker, honestly surprised. “I thought
everybody knew.” “I don’t.” “Why—” she said hesitantly. “Tom’s got some woman in New York.”
“Got some woman?” I repeated blankly. Miss Baker nodded.
“She might have the decency not to telephone him at dinner time.
Don’t you think?” Almost before I had grasped her meaning
there was the flutter of a dress and the crunch of leather boots, and Tom and
Daisy were back at the table.
“It couldn’t be helped!” cried Daisy with tense gaiety.
She sat down, glanced searchingly at Miss Baker and then at me, and continued: “I
looked outdoors for a minute, and it’s very romantic outdoors. There’s a bird in
the lawn that I think might be a nightingale come over on the Cunard or
White Star Line. He’s singing away—” Her voice sang: “It’s romantic, isn’t it, Tom?”
“Very romantic,” he said, and then miserably to me: “If it’s light enough after dinner,
I want to take you down to the stables.” The telephone rang inside, startlingly,
and as Daisy shook her head decisively at Tom the subject of the Staples in
fact all subjects, vanished into air.
Among the broken fragments of the last five minutes at table I remembered the
candles being lit again, pointlessly, and I was conscious of wanting to look
squarely at everyone, and yet to avoid all eyes.
I couldn’t guess what Daisy and Tom were thinking, but I doubt if even Miss Baker,
who seemed to have mastered a certain hearty skepticism was able utterly to
put this fifth guest’s shrill metallic urgency out of mind.
To a certain temperament the situation might have seemed intriguing—
—my own instinct was to telephone immediately for the police.
The horses, needless to say, were not mentioned again. Tom and Miss Baker, with
several feet of twilight between them, strolled back into the library, as if to
a vigil beside a perfectly tangible body, while, trying to look pleasantly
interested in a little death I followed Daisy around a chain of connecting
verandas to the porch in front.
In its deep gloom we sat down side by side on a wicker City Daisy took her
face in her hands as if feeling its lovely shape, and her eyes moved
gradually out into that velvet dusk.
I saw that turbulent emotions possessed her, so I asked what I thought would be some
sedative questions about her little girl.
“We don’t know each other very well, Nick,” she said suddenly. “Even if we are cousins.
You didn’t come to my wedding.” “I wasn’t back from the war.” “That’s true.”
She hesitated.
“Well, I’ve had a very bad time, Nick, and I’m pretty cynical about everything.”
Evidently she had reason to be.
I waited but she didn’t say anymore and after a moment I returned rather feebly
to the subject of her daughter. “I suppose she talks, and— —eats, and everything.” “Oh, yes.”
She looked at me absently. “Listen, Nick; let me tell you what I said when she was born.
Would you like to hear?” “Very much.” “It’ll show you how I’ve gotten to feel about—
—things.
Well, she was less than an hour old and Tom was God knows where.
I woke up out of the ether with an utterly abandoned feeling, and asked the
nurse right away if it was a boy or a girl.
She told me it was a girl, and so I turned my head away and wept.
‘All right,’ I said, ‘I’m glad it’s a girl.
And I hope she’ll be a fool— —that’s the
best thing a girl can be in this world, a beautiful little fool.’
“You see I think everything’s terrible anyhow,” she went on in a convinced way.
“Everybody thinks so— —the most advanced people. And I know I’ve been everywhere
and seen everything and done everything.” Her eyes flashed around her in a defiant way,
rather like toms and she laughed with thrilling scorn. “Sophisticated— —God, I’m sophisticated!”
The instant her voice broke off, ceasing to compel my attention, my belief, I felt
the basic insincerity of what she had said.
It made me uneasy, as though the whole evening had been a trick of some sort to
extract a contributory emotion from me.
I waited, and sure enough, in a moment she looked at me with an absolute smirk on
her lovely face, as if she had asserted her membership in a rather distinguished
secret society to which she and Tom belonged.
Inside, the crimson Rune ballooned with light.
Tom and Miss Baker sat at either end of the long couch and she read aloud to him
from the Saturday Evening Post —the words, murmurous and uninflected,
running together in a soothing tune.
The lamp light bright on his boots and dull on the Autumn Leaf yellow of her
hair, glinted along the paper as she turned the page with a flutter of
slender muscles in her arms. When we came in she held a silent for a moment with a
lifted hand.
“To be continued,” she said, tossing the magazine on the table, “in our very next
issue.” Her body asserted itself with a restless movement of her knee, and she stood up
10 o’clock shiramar apparently finding the time on the ceiling. “Time for this
good girl to go to bed.” “Jordan’s going to play in the tournament tomorrow,”
explained Daisy, “over at Westchester.” “Oh— —you’re Jordan Baker.”
I knew now why your face was familiar— —its pleasing contemptuous expression had
looked out at me from many rotographer pictures of the sporting life at
Asheville and Hot Springs and Palm Beach.
I had heard some story of her too, a critical, unpleasant story, but what it
was I had forgotten long ago.
“Good night,” she said softly. “Wake me at
eight, won’t you.” “If you’ll get up.” “I will.
Good night, Mr Caraway See you in on Of course you will,” confirmed Daisy. “In fact
I think I’ll arrange a marriage. Come over often, Nick, and I’ll sort of— —oh—
—fling you together. You know— —lock you up accidentally in linen closets and push
you out to see in a boat, and all that sort of thing—”
“Good night,” called Miss Baker from the stairs. “I haven’t heard a word.”
“She’s a nice girl,” said Tom after a moment. “They ought to let her run around
the country this way.” “Who ought into inquired Daisy coldly. “Her family.”
“Her family is one on to about a thousand years old. Besides, Nick’s going to look
after her, aren’t you, Nick? She’s going to spend lots of weekends out here this summer.
I think the home influence will be very good for her.”
Daisy and Tom looked at each other for a moment in silence.
“Is she from New York?” I asked quickly.
“From Louisville. Our white girlhood was passed there. Our beautiful white—” “Did you
give Nick a little heart-to-heart talk on the veranda?” demanded Tom suddenly. “Did
I?” She looked at me. “I can’t seem to remember, but I think we talked about the
Nordic race. Yes, I’m sure we did. It sort
of crept up on us and first thing you know—” “Don’t believe everything you hear,
Nick,” he advised me. I said lightly that I had heard nothing at all, and a few
minutes later I got up to go home.
They came to the door with me and stood side by side in a cheerful square of light.
As I started my motor Daisy peremptorally called: “Wait!
“I forgot to ask you something, and it’s important.
We heard you were engaged to a girl out West.” “That’s right,” corroborated Tom
kindly. “We heard that you were engaged.” “It’s liable I’m too poor.” “But we heard it,”
insisted Daisy, surprising me by opening up again in a flower-like way. “We heard
it from three people, so it must be true.” Of course I knew what they were
referring to, but I wasn’t even vaguely engaged. The fact that gossip had
published the bands was one of the reasons I'd come East. You can’t stop
going with an old friend on account of rumors and on the other hand I had no
intention of being rumored into marriage.
Their interest rather touched me and made them less remotely rich—
—nevertheless, I was confused and a little disgusted as I drove away.
It seemed to me that the thing for Daisy
to do was to rush out of the house, child in arms— —but apparently there was no such
intention in her head.
As for Tom, the fact that he “had some woman in New York” was really less
surprising than that he had been depressed by a book.
Something was making him nibble at the edge of stale ideas as if his sturdy
physical egotism no longer nourished his peremptory heart.
Already it was deep summer on Road House roofs and in front of wayside garages,
where new red gas pump sat out in pools of light,
and when I reached my estate at West Egg
I ran the car under its shed and sat for a while on an abandoned grass roller in
the yard.
The wind had blown off, leaving a loud, bright night, with wings beating in the
trees and a persistent organ sound as the full bellows of the earth blew the
frogs full of life.
The silhouette of a moving cat wavered across the moonlight, and, turning my head
to watch it, I saw that I was not alone 50 feet away a figure had emerged from
the shadow of my neighbor's mansion and was standing with his hands in his
pockets regarding the silver pepper of the stars.
Something in his leisurely movements and the secure position of his feet upon the
lawn suggested that it was Mr. Gatsby himself, come out to determine what Cher
was his of our local heavens.
I decided to call to him. Miss Baker had mentioned him at dinner, and that would
do for an introduction.
But I didn’t call to him, for he gave a sudden intimation that he
was content to be alone— —he stretched out his arms toward the dark water in a curious way
as far as I was from him, I could have sworn he was trembling.
Involuntarily I glanced seaward— —and distinguished nothing except a single
green light, minute and far away, that might have been the end of a dock.
When I looked once more for Gatsby he had vanished, and I was alone again
in the unquiet darkness